

Artist Bio, Artist Statement, & Curriculum Vitae

2905 W Shakespeare Ave Unit 3N, Chicago, IL, 60647 hello@amaykataria.com www.amaykataria.com 646-761-5173

Artist Bio

Amay Kataria (b. New Delhi, India) graduated from the School of the Art Institute of Chicago (2019) with an MFA in Art & Technology Studies. After completing his bachelors in Computer Engineering from Virginia Tech (2012), he worked for Microsoft Corp. (2013-2017) in Seattle, WA. He has been invited as a visiting artist at the Ethereal Summit, ThoughtWorks and Bellas Artes Outpost and was awarded the New Media Art Residency at Art Center Nabi. He has participated in group shows at the Art Institute of Chicago, USA (2017), Experimental Sound Studio, Chicago, USA (2018), Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA (2018), Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea (2018), ThoughtWorks, New York, USA (2018) and Bajaj Bhawan, Mumbai, India (2019). To support his work, he has received grants in the name of Shapiro Level-Up Research Grant and Bajaj Art Scholarship.

Artist Statement

My art practice is deeply rooted in the personal, yet ubiquitous interaction with the world. The poiesis of my work lies in an assemblage of algorithmic instructions as computer code that manifests itself in the form of kinetic imagery, sculptures, and sonic experiences. Currently, it interrogates the posthuman affairs of existence in a society where technology has transformed from a necessity to a socio-political body of governance. It's time based nature, along with a cause and effect system of relations often results in a bidirectional exchange of data and information to surface the work as an interactive rhizomatic experience. In these works, the medium is the instrument of intervention and the content is represented through the filter of my political consciousness of this world. In my recent bodies of work, I have been concerned with concepts like the human behavior as a subject of attention economy, the self-referential nature of coexistence between humans and natural systems, a decentralized commodification strategy of human identity through Blockchain technology, and the influence of ghost labor of bots and agents on the human workforce. Concurrently, I'm departing and arriving on new concerns, which help me unravel my own position within these super structures.

Curriculum Vitae

<u>akataria@saic.edu</u> - <u>www.amaykataria.com</u> - <u>www.github.com/eulphean</u>

Education

MFA, Art & Technology Studies, May 2019

School of the Art Institute of Chicago

Concentration in developing a transdisciplinary, research based art practice to interrogate concepts with new media.

Awards Bajaj Art Scholarship, Shapiro Research Level-Up Grant

B.S., Computer Engineering, December 2012

Virginia Tech

Concentration in embedded systems, hardware-software design, data structures & algorithms, and interdisciplinary product design.

CGPA 3.84, Rank 5/126

Summa Cum Laude

Awards Bernard Silverman, Byron M. & Helen S. Brumback, Gilbert & Lucille Seay, MR. & CP. Staley Memorial, Litton Industries, Benjamin F.Bock, James Milton Beattie Jr.

Skills & Tools

Code C++, Javascript, Python, Java, C#, Solidity, Objective-C, Swift, C

Platforms OpenFrameworks, P5.js, Processing, React/React-Native, Heroku, PostgreSQL, AngularJS, EmberJS, Bootstrap

Boards Arduino, Teensy, Raspberry Pi, Asus Tinker Board, Beaglebone

Kinetics DC/Servo/Stepper motors, Motor Controller, Mechanisms

3D Rhino, Grasshopper, Blender, Unity, 3D printing, Photogrammetry, HoloLens

Sound Audio Digital Signal Processing (DSP), Ableton Live, PureData, MaxMSP

Design Sketch, GIMP, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Adobe After-Effects

Work Experience

Creative Consultant, Amay Kataria, September, 2017 - Current

Freelance creative technology development for new media artists. This includes experience design, creative software development and art installation maintenance. Chicago, IL

Teaching Assistant, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 2017 - 2018
Interactive Art & Intro to Computer Vision and Machine Learning with *Christopher Baker*Kinetics and Computer Control with *Jacob Tonski*Digital Light Projection with *Jan Tichy*

Lab Assistant, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 2017 - 2018 Electronics and Kinetics Lab

Creative Technologist, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, May - July, 2018 Expanded and engineered new Light Kits for Jan Tichy's Digital Light Projection class. This included PCB design and programming a new Arduino library with examples to guide first-time students through digital light production.

Software Engineer II, Microsoft Corp., May 2013 - June 2017 Skype for Consumers, Skype for Business, Window Hyper-V Seattle, WA

Software Engineering Intern, Qualcomm, May 2012 - August 2012 San Diego, California

Systems Solutions Engineering Intern, Harris Corporation, January - August, 2010 Lynchburg, Virginia

Residencies & Workshops

Artist in Residence, Brahman AI, Bombay Beach, California, January 2020 A three week artist in residence in a collaborative community interested in art, technology, machine learning, artificial intelligence and ecology led by Gene Kogan.

Visiting Artist, Hangfarm, Ellend, Hungary, August 2020

A two week workshop and an open-air exhibition space, Meadowscape, for nature-based media art.

Visiting Artist, Bellas Artes Outpost, Manilla, Philippines, June 2019

A two day workshop on Context-Responsive Art Practice with Raqs Media Collective as part of Eskwela, an experimental school for transdisciplinary thought process and art making.

New Media Resident, Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea, July-September 2018

A two month long residency to research the intersection of Art & Blockchain and express it through aesthetic processes.

Visiting Artist, Ethereal Summit, New York City, May 2018

A two day Art & Blockchain conference in New York as part of the maker-space hosted by New York-based artist, Jessica Angel.

Art-A-Hack Resident, ThoughtWorks, New York City, June-July 2018

A one month collaborative residency to investigate the awareness of climate change through the lens of human behavioral psychology.

Creative Commissions

Encryption Archive, New work commission for Dylan Fish Boundless Encounters
HangZhou Triennial of Fiber Art, China, November 2019

Three Ecologies, New work commission for Jaclyn Jacunski Terrain Exhibitions
Terrain Biennial, Chicago, October 2019
Ethereum Farm, New work commission for Stephanie Rothenberg ReThinking Labor
Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA, September 2019
Goodbye Cruel World, It's Over
Weltkunstzimmer, Dusseldorf, Germany

Frayed Continuum, Arduino code to drive motors for Ayesha Singh It Was Never Concrete Shrine Empire, New Delhi, India, August 2019

Long Memory, Arduino code to drive hacked hard drives for Ziv Z'eev Cohen Remanence/Remnants
062 Gallery, Zhoub Art Center, Chicago, USA, August 2019

RGBY, Arduino & Raspberry Pi code to drive Neon for Yaazd Hafeez Contractor NYCxDesign New York City, USA, May 2019

Small-Pop Hypothesis, Electronics & Arduino code for Galen Odell-Smedley MFA Thesis Show 2018 Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA, May 2018

Exhibition History

2020

2 Degree Window Project

Fixity Equals Death curated by Francisca Rudolph Space P11, Chicago, USA January, 2019

2019

Babble Wall
Learning Machines
Electromuseum, Moscow, Russia
December 10, 2019

The Nest & Ontology of Cryptocollectibles
CYBERIA: New Media Playground curated by Anokhi Shah
TIFA Studios, Pune, India
December 13, 2019

Babble Wall & Figments of Attention

Future is Here: Art & Technology in a Millenial Age curated by Dr. Arshiya Lokhandwala Phoenix City Mall, Chennai, India November 28, 2019

2 Degree Window Project
Fixity Equals Death curated by Francisca Rudolph
Wrong Biennale, Chicago, USA
November 1, 2019

The Nest
Always Already Alien curated by John Duncan Bass
Ars Electronica, Linz, Austria
September 5, 2019

Figments of Desire
MFA Thesis Show curated by Rohan Ayinde Smith
Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA
April - June, 2019

Speculative Bitcoin Wallet & Groove Body Student display case curated by Anna Yu Art Institute of Chicago, USA March - April, 2019

Babble Wall & Figments of Attention

Future is Here: Art & Technology in a Millenial Age curated by Dr. Arshiya Lokhandwala Bajaj Bhawan, Mumbai, India January - April, 2019

2018

Groove Body
Nabi Artist Residency 2018 Exhibition
Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea
September - November, 2018

2 Degree Window Project Art-A-Hack Exhibition Thoughtworks, New York City, USA July, 2018

Ontology of Cryptocollectibles
Art & Blockchain Hack Space
Ethereal Summit, New York City, USA
May, 2018

Bad Breath Waveforms Experimental Sound Studio, Chicago, USA April, 2018

Generative Decay
Algomotion
Art Institute of Chicago, USA
May - August, 2018

2017

Parabolic Dish
Creative Coding Exhibition
Art Institute of Chicago, USA
December, 2018 - February, 2018

Tree of Life Interactive Performance Art Institute of Chicago, USA December, 2017

#40, #60 Answering Machine Art Institute of Chicago, USA October, 2017

Public Talks

Autopoiesis, Artist Talk, Art & Technology Studies, SAIC, March 2019

Art x Body x Blockchain, Artist Talk, Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea, August 2018

Github Workshop, Art & Technology Studies, SAIC, November 2017

Publication & Press

Chennaiyil, Experience Art & Technology in the millenial age at Phoenix Market City with the Art Exhibition, 'Future is Here'!, December 3, 2019 [Link]

The New Indian Express, *The art inside the underbelly*, November 28, 2019 [Link]

Times of India, *Art exhibition in Chennai to expose digital realities*, November 25, 2019 [Link]

Ars Electronica, Always Already Alient, September 2019 [Link]

School of the Art Institute of Chicago, *Art & Technology Studies Brochure*, *Groove Body*, August 2019

School of the Art Institute of Chicago, *Grad View Book*, *Small-Pop Hypothesis (Galen Odell-Smedley & Amay Kataria)*, January 2019

The Times of India, *With New-Age Tech, Millennials Shape Art For The Future*, January 17, 2019 [Link]

Indian Express, *An interactive exhibition explores the uses and abuses of digital technology,* January 25, 2019 [Link]

Vogue, How Is Technology Affecting Millennials?, January 17, 2019 [Link]

Art Center Nabi, Blockchain City: Reinventing "I" and Reclaiming "We", November, 2018

Gwangju Ilbo, Dreaming Of A City Of Media Art In Gwangju, October 9, 2018 [Link]

Coindesk Korea, What's Up, Blockchain?, October 16, 2018 [Link]

Coindesk Korea, *My Face Is 'Chained' To The Ethereum Blockchain*, September 28, 2018 [Link]

Blockinpress, *Paying For Art With My Mugshot? Blockchain Meets Art*, September 21, 2018 [<u>Link</u>]

Crown Goose Blog, 'Nabi Artist Residency 2018' Intersection Of Art and Technology, September 14, 2018 [Link]

CoinNews, Blockchain Art, September 5, 2018 [Link]

Blockinpress, *When Blockchain Meets Art; Amay Katria and Matthias Dörfelt*, August 20, 2018 [Link]